<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$
  ======================================================================
-->

<page category="documentation">
<sitemap filename="sitemap.xml"/>
<title>
    Documentation Roadmap
</title>

<text>
  <p>
    Documentation is one of our big problems in this project. If you
    are willing to give us a hand here, you're more than welcome.
  </p><p>
    The available documentation is mostly about index styles and
    <b>xindy</b> concepts. In fact, this was a university research
    project - we have quite some research papers.
  </p><p>
    The upcoming new 2nd edition of the <em>LaTeX Companion</em> will
    describe usage of <b>xindy</b> the easy way, for those who just
    want to have a MakeIndex replacement for usual LaTeX documents.
  </p><p>
  </p>
</text>



<coltext>
<leftcol>
    For Document Authors
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    A simple HOWTO document is not (yet) available. If you use LaTeX,
    your best bet is the 2nd edition of the <em>LaTeX Companion</em>,
    there <b>xindy</b> usage is described in detail. In the future, we
    hope to get permission to use some of this material here as well.
  </p><p>
    The <a href="doc/faq.html">FAQ</a> has also some questions and
    answers about <b>xindy</b>'s command line interface, that might be
    of interest for you.
  </p><p>
    If your index is more complex than references to some page
    numbers, you might want to read the <a
    href="doc/tutorial.html"><b>xindy</b> Tutorial</a>, since you will
    need to write your own index style.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>


<coltext>
<leftcol>
    For Style Writers
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    As an introduction, you should start with the <a
    href="doc/tutorial.html"><b>xindy</b> Tutorial</a> to learn about
    basic <b>xindy</b> concepts.
  </p><p>
    The <a href="doc/faq.html">FAQ</a> is
    especially useful for the TeX community answering many common
    questions.
  </p><p>
    Eventually, you will have to look into the <a
    href="doc/manual.html"><b>xindy</b> Reference Manual</a>, though.
    However, study some of the examples first.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>


<coltext>
<leftcol>
    Reference Docs
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <dl>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/manual.html"><b>xindy</b> Reference Manual</a>
    </dt>
    <dd>
      is the definitive description of all xindy declarations, used to
      specify sorting, character classes, locations, markup, etc. Our
      feedback is that the used reference language uses too much Lisp
      jargon, without that knowledge you will have to spend a few
      additional hours to get aquainted to.
      <p>
	Before you read it, have a look at the <a
	href="doc/tutorial.html"><b>xindy</b> Tutorial</a>. The <a
	href="doc/xindy-tr.pdf"><b>xindy</b> Technical Report</a> (in
	Postscript) is also a good preparation to learn about the
	models behind <b>xindy</b>.
      </p>
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="make-rules.html"><b>make-rules</b> Documentation</a>
    </dt>
    <dd>
      details which languages are supported.
    </dd>
  </dl>
</rightcol>
</coltext>


<coltext>
<leftcol>
    Technical Reports
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    Please note that some of the reports contain outdated contact, Web
    Site, and download information.
  </p>
  <dl>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/xindy-eurotex98.pdf"><b>xindy</b> - A Flexible
      Indexing System</a> (PDF)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Presented at EuroTeX 98, St. Malo, France; awarded best
      conference paper. Cahiers GUTenberg Vol. 28-29, March 1998, p.
      223-230.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/xindy-tr.pdf"><b>xindy</b>: Definition of an
      Indexing Model and its Implementation</a> (PDF)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Technical Report TI-11/1997, Technical University of Darmstadt
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/xindy-tr-cbm.pdf">A Simple Context-Based Markup
      Algorithm and its Efficient Implementation in CLOS</a> (PDF)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Technical Report TI-12/1997, Technical University of Darmstadt
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/new-sort-rules.ps">Sorting Index Entries with
      <b>xindy</b> revisited</a> (in Postscript, also as <a
      href="doc/new-sort-rules.ps.gz">.ps.gz</a>)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Describes the current implementation scheme with examples from
      German and French sorting.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/sort-rules.html">Draft discussion paper on
      International Sorting</a> (also in <a
      href="doc/sort-rules.ps">Postscript</a> and in <a
      href="doc/sort-rules.ps.gz">.ps.gz</a>)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Musings that lead to the revisited index sorting scheme, as
      described in the previous report. Since these musings have some
      interesting guidelines and report about pitfalls, we have kept
      them online.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="doc/xindy-studienarbeit.pdf"><b>xindy</b> - Ein
      Flexibles Indexierungssystem</a>, Studienarbeit FB Informatik,
      TH-Darmstadt, November 1995 (PDF, in German).
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Roger's original report on his student project.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC22/WG20/">ISO/IEC 14651
      International String Ordering</a> (external link)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      This ISO Standard was used in creation of the <b>xindy</b> sort
      mechanism. The Web site referred above still has the final draft
      online, in Wordperfect format. It also has some sorting rules
      online, in the documents section.
    </dd>
  </dl>
</rightcol>
</coltext>


</page>
