<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$
  ======================================================================
-->

<page category="download">
<sitemap filename="sitemap.xml"/>
<title>
    Download Source
</title>

<text>
  <div class="quotation">
    You are in a maze of twisty little passages, all alike...
    <address>-- Adventure</address>
  </div>
  <p>
    If you are looking for a standard Source distribution with
    <em>configure; make; make install</em> - this is not your project.
    But if you are willing to plunge into a challenge, <b>xindy</b> is
    something for you.
  </p><p>
    Full source for <b>xindy</b> is available, but currently it is
    quite hard to build <b>xindy</b> from source. This page was
    written by <a href="mailto:jschrod@acm.org">Joachim Schrod</a>. It
    shall report what's available and shall provide information how to
    create <b>xindy</b> from source.
  </p><p>
    <b>xindy</b> is written in Common Lisp. <a
    href="http://clisp.cons.org/">CLISP</a> has been used for
    development.
  </p><p>
  </p>
</text>


<coltext>
<leftcol>
  xindy Structure
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    <b>xindy</b> consists of (1) plugins for a Common Lisp system,
    (2) Common Lisp code that makes up the <b>xindy</b> kernel, and
    (3) <b>xindy</b> modules.
  </p><p>
    To create <b>xindy</b>, one needs to integrate the plugins into a
    Common Lisp system. We did this for <a
    href="http://clisp.cons.org/">CLISP</a>, the result are the
    platform-specific archives on the <a
    href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=10646&amp;release_id=52566">software
    distribution page</a>.
  </p><p>
    Then, the <b>xindy</b> kernel source code is compiled, and a final
    executable is created. In the case of CLISP, the executable
    consists of two files, a virtual machine and a memory image.
  </p><p>
    <b>xindy</b> module code is interpreted at run time.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  Download
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    The <a
    href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=10646">Download
    Area</a> is at SourceForge.
  </p><p>
    Fetch
    <ol>
      <li><a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/xindy/xindy-2.1.tar.gz?download"><tt>xindy-2.1.tar.gz</tt></a></li>
      <li><a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/xindy/xindy-clisp-modules-2001-04-10.tar.bz2?download"><tt>xindy-clisp-modules-2001-04-10.tar.bz2</tt></a></li>
    </ol>
  </p><p>
    You've got the complete source. If you want to work on
    <b>xindy</b>, we recommend the CVS source.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  CVS: the real source
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    The real source is available by anonymous CVS, as explained on our
    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=10646">SourceForge
    project CVS page</a>. We welcome new developers and will give out
    commit rights quickly.
  </p><p>
    Three top-level CVS modules exist: <tt>xindy</tt> is the kernel
    source code, <tt>make-rules</tt> is used to create <b>xindy</b>
    language modules, and <tt>www</tt> is the XML source code for this
    Web Site.
  </p><p>
    The CVS module <tt>xindy</tt> also has source code of the
    documentation and the reports. The documentation is written in
    SGML, with <i>linuxdoc</i>. It shall be migrated to DocBook. The
    reports are written in LaTeX, of course.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  Common Lisp plugins
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    There are two plugins: <i>ordrules</i> which implements string
    ordering rules, and <i>regexp</i> which implements regular
    expressions. The plugins have been introduced for reuse
    (<i>ordrules</i> comes from a predecessor project,
    <i>International MakeIndex</i>) and for performance reasons
    (remember, <b>xindy</b> was written in 1995).
  </p><p>
    Frankly, today I consider the usage of plugins as a very big
    error. They should be replaced by ``pure'' Lisp solutions as soon
    as possible - currently, they are the big porting nightmare of
    <b>xindy</b>.
  </p><p>
    We used <a href="http://clisp.cons.org/">CLISP</a> as the Common
    Lisp system for development. But CLISP changed its plugin API some
    time ago. Thus it is not possible to integrate the plugin modules
    into current CLISP distributions. Nobody has adapted the plugins
    to the new API yet. Of course, we would welcome such a
    contribution. But if you're proficient enough in Common Lisp,
    rewriting it in Lisp might be even easier and would be as welcome.
  </p><p>
    Roger Kehr reported a succesful <b>xindy</b> port to ACL. More
    information on that port is unknown.
  </p><p>
    The plugin sources are also in the CVS module <tt>xindy/rx</tt>.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  Source access, revisited
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    Ignore the CVS module <tt>xindy/src</tt>, that's a relict that is
    explained below.
  </p><p>
    <b>xindy</b> was written with the help of <a
    href="http://www.eecs.harvard.edu/~nr/noweb/"><i>noweb</i></a>, a
    Literate Programming System. <a
    href="http://www.kitebird.com/imake-book/"><i>Imake</i></a> was
    used for abstract dependency descriptions. The test suite is
    realized by <a
    href="http://www.gnu.org/directory/dejagnu.html"><i>DejaGnu</i></a>.
    You need to get these systems before you start. You need only the
    <tt>imake</tt> executable, not the dreaded MIT X configuration
    files. Use <tt>tools/imkmf</tt> as command line interface for
    <i>Imake</i>.
  </p><p>
    <tt>xindy/xindy/intro.nw</tt> has an introduction into code
    structure and conventions.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  Ancient version
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    <b>xindy</b> was written first in 1995, as student project by
    Roger Kehr, under supervision of <a
    href="mailto:jschrod@acm.org">Joachim Schrod</a>. The source of
    this student project is in the CVS module <tt>xindy/src</tt>. I
    don't know if this code does still run at all.
  </p><p>
    Starting in 1996, Roger did a rewrite of the sorting rules, to add
    support for sorting phases. You'll find more information on this
    in the technical reports. At this time, he also restructured the
    source and placed each module in its own directory. Furthermore,
    he added the test suite.
  </p><p>
    The ancient version will be relegated to a CVS branch, and shall
    be removed from the main trunk.
  </p>
</rightcol>
</coltext>

<coltext>
<leftcol>
  Build recipes
</leftcol>
<rightcol>
  <p>
    I have found two Web pages with information how to build
    <b>xindy</b>. Due to the change in the CLISP plugin API, the
    information from these pages is not literally valid any more; but
    the basic process is described correctly.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The platform-specific archives from the 2.1 distribution were
      created by <a
      href="mailto:thenlich@users.sourceforge.net">Thomas Henlich</a>
      with <a href="source-build-thomas.html">this build process</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Roger wrote up <a href="source-build-roger.html">this
      description</a> in 1999.
    </li>
  </ul>
</rightcol>
</coltext>


<prev url="download-binary.html">Binary Distributions</prev>
<next
url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=10646&amp;release_id=52566">SourceForge
Download Area</next>



</page>
